And this is the first time that we'll be coding against our big project of the course.
이 과정의 큰 프로젝트에 대해 코딩하는 건 이번이 처음이죠
Welcome to Jupyter Lab.
주피터 연구소에 잘 오셨어요
Welcome to the week six folder as we embark upon our big project.
6주 차 폴더에 오신 걸 환영합니다 큰 프로젝트에 착수했죠
So again, our project is to build a model that can estimate how much something costs based on the description
그래서 우리 프로젝트는 제품 설명에 근거해 가격을 추정할 수 있는 모델을 만드는
of the product.
거죠
And today we're going to be doing the first step in data curation.
오늘은 데이터 큐레이션의 첫 단계를 할 거예요
And we'll start by looking at a subset of the data for home appliances, washing machines and the like.
우선 가정용 가전제품이나 세탁기 같은 가전제품의 데이터부터 살펴보죠
So first let me just show you the data set itself.
먼저 데이터 집합을 보여드릴게요
The data set is is at this link right here.
데이터 집합은 이 링크에 있어요
This is the data set on the hugging face datasets section of the Hugging Face hub.
이건 안아주는 얼굴 허브의 안아주는 얼굴 데이터셋 섹션의 데이터셋이에요
Um, and it is a series of um, of scraped Amazon reviews that that goes back in time.
아마존에서 조사한 리뷰의 일련인데 그 시대를 거슬러 올라가죠
But this latest scrape that was from 20 was from late 2023.
하지만 20년에 생긴 이 잔해는 2023년 말에 생긴 거예요
Um, it contains a huge number of reviews, but it also contains almost 50 million items in there.
리뷰도 엄청나게 많이 실렸고 거의 5천만 개의 아이템이 실려 있어요
So there's a lot of different products and they're divided into these different categories.
다양한 제품이 있고 여러 카테고리로 나뉘어 있어요
We are not going to be working with all of these.
이걸 다 가지고는 일 못 해요
We're going to pluck out a subset of this that are the kinds of categories that interest us the most
여기서 일부를 추출할 겁니다 이 훈련에 가장 흥미로운
for this exercise.
범주예요
Otherwise, everything would take an awfully long time to train and that wouldn't be any fun.
안 그러면 훈련하는 데 너무 오래 걸려서 재미가 없을 거예요
So this gives you a good sense of the kind of data that we're working with.
우리가 작업하는 데이터의 종류에 대한 좋은 감각을 제공하죠
And if I go into the folder, the hugging face folder that contains the data for what, what the dataset
안는 얼굴 폴더로 들어가 볼게요. 메타데이터가 들어있는 폴더입니다. 제품과
calls meta data, which is the data of the products and descriptions and prices themselves, which is
설명, 가격에 대한 데이터입니다. 우리가 정말 신경 쓰는 것들이죠.
Here it is.
여기 있네요
And you can get a good sense if you look at the data set for things like electronics, you can see that
좋은 감을 잡을 수 있어요 전자 제품의 데이터 세트를 보면요 크기가 5기가바이트
it's just over five gigabytes in size.
조금 넘는 걸 보실 수 있어요
So these are big data sets and they're going to have a ton of useful information.
빅데이터 집합이죠 유용한 정보가 엄청나게 많아요
And it was uploaded seven months ago.
7개월 전에 업로드됐고요
So this is all quite recent.
최근 일이군요
So let's get going.
Get up, Get up, Get up, Get up, Get, 시작, 시작할게요
We begin with some imports.
수입 문제부터 시작하죠
Nothing particularly complicated there.
복잡할 게 없죠
Not as yet.
아직은요
There will be more to come.
더 많이 올 거예요
Uh, we're going to set up our environment.
환경을 설정할 거예요
Not that we're going to be using any of this today.
오늘 이걸 쓸 건 아니지만요
We're just going to be using hugging face.
그냥 껴안는 얼굴만 할 거예요
Log in to hugging face.
얼굴 포옹에 로그인하세요
Um, and, uh, this this makes sure that, uh, matplotlib can show us charts in the Jupyter notebook.
매트플로틀리브가 유피터 노트북에 차트를 띄울 수 있게 해 주죠
So the first thing to do is to load in our data set.
먼저 데이터 세트를 로드해요
And what we're going to do is we specify the name of the data set, Amazon reviews.
우리가 할 일은 데이터 집합의 이름을 지정하는 겁니다 Amazon reviews요
And we're going to just choose to start with the appliances category.
어플라이언스 카테고리로 시작하도록 선택할게요
Appliances home appliances like like uh fridges and, and uh, washing machines and the like, um,
냉장고나 세탁기 같은 가전제품을 가장 먼저 로드할 거예요
are going to be the first things that we're going to load in using hugging faces load data set, uh,
얼굴 포옹 데이터 로드셋 함수를 이용해서요
Um, and the first time you run this, it will actually download it from the Huggingface hub, since
이걸 처음 실행하면 H깅페이스 허브에서 다운로드 됩니다
I've already done that, that won't be required for me.
제가 이미 했기 때문에 그건 필요 없죠
It will just bring in and this has already completed and we'll see how many appliances we have.
이미 완성된 가전제품이 몇 개나 있는지 확인할 거예요
We have 94,000 home appliances in there.
가전제품이 94,000개 있어요
So let's have a look at one of these guys.
이 중 하나를 보죠
Let's have a look at uh let's say data point equals data set.
어디 보자 데이터 포인트가 데이터셋이라고 해보죠
Let's take the first one.
첫 번째 걸 보죠
Why not.
안 될 거 없죠
Let's have a look at it.
한번 보죠
So this is what it looks like.
이렇게 생긴 거군요
It's got tons of information.
정보가 아주 많아요
But in particular you can see it has something called features.
하지만 특히 기능이라는 게 있어요
It has a title and it has a few other things that are probably going to be useful for us.
제목도 있고 몇 가지 다른 것도 있는데 아마 유용할 거예요
And in particular it has a title, a description, features, details and price.
특히 제목, 설명, 기능 세부 사항, 가격이 있죠
Let's just print each of them out so we can have a quick look.
하나씩 프린트해서 잠깐 보도록 하죠
So this is the title.
이게 제목이에요
This is an ice maker machine countertop.
얼음 제조기 조리대예요
This is its description which is empty.
이 묘사는 비어 있어요
This is its details.
이게 세부 사항이에요
So features lots of features, details here and price which we immediately see a problem.
기능이 아주 많아요 상세 정보와 가격은 문제가 바로 보이네요
Price is none in this case.
이 경우엔 프라이스가 없어요
So clearly not all of the items have a price.
모든 물건에 가격이 있는 건 아니군요
And you'll notice that description appears to come in the form of a list.
보다시피 설명은 목록의 형태로 나타나죠
So A features whereas details comes in the form of a dictionary.
특성이라면 세부 사항은 사전 형태로 나오겠죠
Although that is deceiving, it's actually not a dictionary.
그건 속임수지만 사전은 아니에요
It is a string that contains JSON.
JSON을 포함하는 문자열이죠
So this is text that if we want to read into that, we would need to load that in and use A and convert
이 텍스트를 읽어내려면 로드 인을 하고 A를 써서 사전으로 변환해야 해요 JSON
it into a dictionary using JSON load string load s.
로드 문자열 로드 s를 써서요
Um, okay.
네
Let's look at a different data point just to see the next one.
다른 데이터 포인트를 보고 다음 걸 보죠
Looks like an egg holder for a refrigerator, uh, and holds up to ten eggs also none.
냉장고 달걀꽂이처럼 생겼고 달걀 10개까지 들어가며 하나도 없어요
No price for that one either.
이것도 가격은 없어요
And this third one doesn't have a price either.
세 번째도 가격표가 없어요
It's a brand new dryer drum slide.
새 건조기 드럼 슬라이드예요
So at this point we might have our first moment of being concerned.
이 시점에서 처음으로 걱정하게 될지도 몰라요
We've got 94,000 appliances.
가전제품이 94,000개예요
The first three that we've looked at don't have a price.
처음 본 세 개는 가격이 없었어요
So let's see how many do have a price.
몇 개나 가격이 적혀 있는지 보죠
So a simple way to do that is we will iterate through all of the data points in our data set.
간단한 방법은 데이터 집합의 모든 데이터 포인트를 반복하는 거죠
And we will get the price.
Get it, get it, get it, it! 그럼 우린 돈을 벌겠죠
And we will put that in a try block.
그걸 try 블록에 넣을 거예요
Because if it doesn't have one, it will fail and we will just skip that data point.
그게 없으면 실패할 테니까요 그럼 데이터 포인트를 건너뛰죠
So we'll also ignore anything that is priced at zero.
0으로 매기는 것도 전부 무시하고요
So we're just going to be looking at things that have a price that is a number.
따라서 가격이란 숫자가 있는 것만 살펴볼 거예요
And that that price is non-zero is more than zero.
가격이 0이 아닌 0이 0보다 크다는 거죠
I don't think there are any negative prices in there, but if there are, they're not going to get counted.
마이너스 가격은 없을 것 같지만 있다 해도 개수는 확인 안 할 거예요 get it
So this is now going to be going through and trying to figure that out.
이제 이걸 통해 그걸 알아내려 할 거예요
And there we go.
다 됐어요
So it tells us that there are 726, which is almost 50%.
726개라는 뜻인데 거의 50%에 해당하죠
So it's not terrible.
그러니 끔찍하진 않죠
That's fine, that's fine.
괜찮아요, 괜찮아요
It's, uh, for a moment might be worried that there would be a, that it would be slim pickings, but
잠시 걱정되는 건 살 게 별로 없을까 봐서요 하지만 적어도
no, at least for the appliances.
가전제품은 걱정 안 해요
Um, uh, data set, half of them have prices.
데이터 세트인데 절반은 가격이 적혀 있어요
It's a tiny side point.
작은 측면이죠
I don't know if you've spotted when I've been printing numbers.
제가 숫자를 인쇄한 때를 눈치채셨는지 모르겠네요
Generally, they've had a comma to separate the thousands, which I always find so useful when when
보통 쉼표로 수천을 구분하는데 이런 걸 읽을 때
being able to read these kinds of things.
아주 유용하죠
The way that you do that is, if you're using Python's f strings, you say colon comma like this.
이렇게 하는 방법은 파이썬의 f 문자열을 사용한다면: 콤마를 합니다 이렇게요
Um, to you use that for your formatting and then you'll get numbers in this style.
get을 서식에 사용하면 이런 스타일로 숫자가 나와요
Just a little a hot tip.
팁을 하나 드리죠
Uh, you may have known that already, but if not, it's a useful one to be aware of.
어, 이미 알고 계실 수도 있지만 모르셨더라도 알아두면 유용한 정보죠
Okay.
네
So what we're going to do now is we're going to take all of the ones with prices.
이제 할 일은 가격이 있는 건 전부 다 가져오는 거예요
Um, and we're going to figure out how many characters it has in its title, description, features
제목, 설명, 특징, 세부 사항에 글자가 몇 개인지 알아낼 거예요
We're going to add up the total number of characters and put that into a list of lengths.
문자의 총수를 더해서 set의 길이에 입력할 거예요
So what we now have is a list of prices and a list of lengths, so we can get a sense of how how many
이제 가격 목록과 길이 목록이 나왔어요 디테일이 얼마나 많은지 가늠할 수 있죠
characters of detail we have and see if it's uniform or if it's something that's that's in some way
균일한지, 아니면 뭔가 어떤 식으로든 삐뚤어졌는지 알 수 있어요
So now we're going to use matplotlib, which we'll be using a lot, uh, to make a plot of the lengths
그래서 매트플로틀리브를 많이 사용할 거예요 길이를 히스토그램 형태로
in the form of a histogram.
줄거리를 만들 거예요
And hopefully you remember from statistics classes of some time ago, a histogram is basically going
기억하시면 좋겠네요 얼마 전 통계학 클래스에서 히스토그램은 기본적으로
to take everything and bucket it into into bins and show how many we have in each bin.
모든 걸 통에 버킷으로 넣는 거예요 각 통에 몇 개가 있는지 보여주죠
It's easier to show you what that looks like.
직접 보여드리는 게 더 쉽겠네요
This is what it looks like.
이렇게 생겼어요
So along the x axis we have the lengths of our different, um, uh, appliances, our different washing
엑스 축을 따라 각기 다른 가전제품과 세탁기의 길이를 표시합니다
machines or whatever, uh, in terms of how many characters they have in that description.
설명에 포함된 글자의 개수죠
And this is the count of how many appliances do we have with that many characters.
이 정도로 많은 글자를 가진 기기가 몇 개인지 세어보죠
And you can see that there's a nice kind of peak around here, but there is this long tail of more characters
이 주변이 봉우리처럼 솟아 있는데 긴 꼬리가 더
coming in now.
많이 나타나요
This is going to be a challenge for us when we're training, because ultimately we're going to want
이건 우리가 훈련할 때 도전이 될 겁니다 궁극적으로 우리
to use our own, uh, open source models and train them.
자신의 오픈 소스 모델을 사용하고 훈련해야 하니까요
And one of the constraints that's very important for us to understand is the maximum number of characters
우리가 이해해야 하는 중요한 제약 중 하나는 통과할 수 있는 글자 수의 최대치입니다
that we might pass in, or actually the maximum number of tokens that we might pass in to the model
혹은 각 시점에서 통과할 수 있는 토큰의 최대치죠
And the more tokens that we might need to pass in for each of our training points, the more memory
훈련 포인트를 통과할 때마다 메모리가 더 많이 필요하고
that we need for training and the harder it is to achieve.
달성하기 더 어려워져요
Another point is that even when we're using frontier models, whilst they don't have that problem,
또 다른 요점은 개척자 모델을 사용해도 이와 관련된 문제는 없지만 다른 문제가
they have a different problem, which is that it's more expensive if we're passing in more tokens than
있다는 것입니다 토큰을 많이 제출하는 것이 더 많은 토큰을 제출하는
they are going to of course cost us more, which doesn't really mean very much for a for a few of these.
것보다 비용이 더 많이 듭니다 이 문제는 몇몇의 경우에 큰 문제가 되지 않죠
But if we want to do this in anger for a large number of products, then the numbers will start to add
하지만 분노로 많은 제품을 공격한다면 그 숫자는 점점 늘어날 거예요
So ideally we would pick a cutoff and we would constrain our data at that point.
이상적으로는 컷오프를 선택하고 그 시점에서 데이터를 제한하는 거죠
Um, and so that's something that we'll be thinking about later.
그건 나중에 생각해 볼 거예요
Another thing for us to look at is the distribution of the prices.
또 하나 주목할 점은 가격 분배예요
So how much do things cost?
그래서 가격이 얼마죠?
You may have gotten the hint from our earlier analysis that whilst we thought appliances was going to
아까 분석에서 힌트를 얻으셨을 거예요 냉장고나 세탁기
be full of fridges and washing machines and the like, the things that we looked at were rather smaller.
같은 가전제품이 가득할 줄 알았는데 우리가 본 건 좀 더 작았어요
They were egg holders and ice makers, and it shouldn't be that much of a surprise when you think about
달걀 홀더와 제빙기였어요 생각해 보면 그리 놀랍지 않아요
it, that the data is probably going to have a very large number of cheaper things that might sort of,
데이터에 따르면 값싼 제품들이 훨씬 더 많이 있었을 거예요 비싼
um, squash out some of the higher priced items.
제품들을 눌러 버렸겠죠
So let's see that.
한 번 보죠
Let's see how this looks.
어떤지 보죠
Well, that does appear to be the case.
그런 것 같네요
So the average price in our data set is $6.
데이터 집합의 평균 가격은 6달러예요
The highest price is $21,000.
최고 21,000달러까지 올라가요
There is a home appliance for $21,000 in this list, but you can see that there's a very large number
목록에 21,000달러짜리 가전제품이 있는데 가격이 낮은
that have smaller prices.
제품들이 아주 많아요
And for those that remember the difference between mean, median and mode.
중간값과 모드 차이를 기억하시는 분들을 위해 설명드리죠
Again, from school statistics, this is a nice illustration of where the mean can be pulled up by expensive
학교 통계를 보면 비싼 아이템을 기준으로 평균값을 올릴
items and is clearly going to be bigger than, well, certainly than the mode and and probably the median
수 있고 확실히 모드를 능가합니다 중앙값도 능가하겠죠
Uh, so, um, yes, you can you can certainly see we have skewed distribution where there is a very
보시다시피 저렴한 제품이 많이 유통되고 삐뚤게
large number of cheap products.
분배돼 있어요
And that might be challenging during training because the training data is going to be really crowded
훈련 중에는 힘들 수도 있어요 훈련 데이터가 저비용 아이템으로 인해
out by these low cost items.
정말 좁아질 테니까요
Let's just have a quick look for this super expensive thing and see what it is.
이 엄청나게 비싼 물건이 뭔지 빨리 살펴보죠
This this $21,000, uh, item.
21,000달러짜리 물건이에요
We will go through our data set and pluck out whatever it is that costs more than $21,000.
데이터 세트에서 21,000달러 이상 하는 건 다 골라낼 거예요
It is, it seems, a turbochef bullet.
터보셰프 총알 같아요
Rapid cook electric microwave convection oven.
급속 조리 전자레인지 대류식 오븐이에요
Now, if someone had told me that description, I would never have thought that that was going to cost
누가 그런 설명을 해줬다면 그게 21,000달러나 할 줄은
$21,000.
상상도 못 했을 거예요
I did find something not identical, but something that I think is probably the latest version in Amazon
똑같은 건 아니지만 아마존 최신 버전인 것 같아요
And if we go over to have a look at this, you can see here this is also made by Turbochef.
이걸 자세히 보면 이것도 터보셰프에서 만든 거예요
It's a bargain price of only $18,000, not $21,000.
21,000달러가 아니라 18,000달러밖에 안 해요
But I don't know about you.
당신은 어떤지 모르겠네요
I had no idea that microwaves could cost this much, but it's clearly a very professional microwave,
전자레인지가 이렇게 비싼지 몰랐어요 하지만 전문가용이고
a very high end microwave, and going, as I say, for that bargain price.
고급 전자레인지예요 가격도 저렴하고요
That is the $21,000 version of that is over here somewhere in our way off the scale in our data.
그것의 21,000달러 버전이 여기 어딘가에 있어요 우리 데이터에서 스케일을 벗어나서요
So it's now time for us to curate our data, and we'll do that in the next video.
이제 데이터를 큐레이팅할 시간입니다 다음 비디오에서 하죠